hi pedro thank you so much for
making time for this conversation i've
been looking forward to it all week
and um for me it's it's a it's really an
honor to to have this opportunity to
talk to you because
um i see you personally as one of those
um free radicals
you know a free radical in a in a
chemical reaction
um is a small very small molecule but
it's
it creates chain reactions and
transforms
the the wider context and and when when
i
from what i know about your work in so
many different areas you've been
um as you just said when we had a quick
quick conversation before this
like you always work in networks and you
always work in collaboration with others
but
through that collaborative attitude
you've
you've achieved a huge amount with
others
and um so thank you so much for for this
opportunity and
i normally start with um inviting people
to tell a little bit about
their story um what what called you
to do this work and how did you start
off in all this well thank you very much
daniel
what a what a gift um
every time i have to
respond to that question it leads me to
to the essence and uh
i know i'm a entrepreneur by nature
got no idea why it happened when i was
very young
an adolescent you know with school kids
we started
uh uh movements youth movements
uh basically music for you youth and
uh and the the result
of that movement was to basically listen
to miss
to music but integrating kids from
public and private schools and
uh and that was way back i mean that was
when i was 14 15.
17 and it you know music for youth and
bonus series has already celebrated its
50th anniversary
so um by the way we had daniel barrymore
at the main avenue uh conducting the
berlin
philharmonia so to celebrate the the
movement
but anyway um um
so so that's me by nature now
unfortunately for my own life
and my society um
you know we went through dictatorships
and um
in my case it affected many of my
most dearest friends
many of them were active
participants of the church movements
and parishes and um
and some actually got into the guerrilla
movements
but i was a friend you see so and and we
coincided in the kind of vision we had
for more equality
and and in those times for more
participation
and um but it happened to be that
uh some went through violence and some
stayed more in the peaceful you know
parts in my case i was much more engaged
with the peace
the the latter but my best friend
roberto from children
[Music]
he was he decided to go for this other
bar
and um and i was sure that he was going
to disappear which was the case in
argentina people were not
executed formally they didn't go through
a trial
they were basically disappeared right
and uh over 30 000 uh
people disappeared right so um
so the night before i was completely
convinced that that was going to be the
last
day i was going to see him there was no
chance
that i that he could sleep at his
parents place
so i just told him come over to my place
you know automatically
and that was the moment that we
actually had the most i had my most
profound conversation in life
and uh i asked him
to do his best to leave the country that
everything
was organized the next day to help him
leave the country he said no way
he said if i do that
i will not be consistent with my values
my vision of change and
um everything that i've said until now
um
will not have any more um
like you know the the the strength
of the language and and and and the
and the value propositions so what
happened
was that i said well um
what can i do for you and he said two
things
tell everybody that i never killed
anyone
and two um
uh well basically um
do everything that you can
to be consistent with what you
think the world should be
yeah so
and the next day my mum had prepared the
most
extraordinary breakfast for him
and we just said you know i i went to
the
to the elevator and said well basically
until next life and that was it
so that was my most profound
conversation
essential conversation that after that
he disappeared but then um
i went down to patagonia just in case
and there was a huge snowstorm
and i i always understood that snow
that snow's storm as like my protection
and after three weeks of snow
you know when we all know what happens
the sun's
light starts shining and you start
seeing you know the brightness
and i felt the feeling of
the opportunity and of hope
but it was the moment that i didn't know
what to do
in my life i had just graduated from law
school both of us
both of us had graduated and when i
graduated i didn't know what to do you
know because i needed to be consistent
with what the law tells you to do
and uh so so
basically i started during those years
this is 1977.
it started wondering well who's going to
be protecting
the beauty of this perfection that i'm
witnessing
of nature with human beings and that was
the
most incipient sense of
an intercourse that i had to devote
my my life to integrate
the earth into everything else
so and that during those times it led me
to
study environmental law and policy
actually abroad
and and comparative uh
policies and law and then when i
returned back
to democracy in argentina in 1982
we started an organization
a local organization but with a latin
american
commitment and engagement so everything
that we would do
would have to create value for the
region
so during those terms my personal
uh identity was very much a latin
american
and coming from this was the foundation
that's right it's uh the environment and
natural resources foundation
that we started with uh a very
prestigious
uh uh expert on natural resources
law and and then from then on
we started doing you know the kind of uh
things that actually you know moved me
and
and i was passionate about which was to
connect
the three axis you know access to
justice access to decision making and
access to
information to environmental
rights so that was actually promoted
into the different national
constitutions and different latin
american countries
and also practicing you know the only
way that you can
promote an idea is that once you have
the tool
that makes that idea tangible and
material
so uh that's basically that period of my
time
that um well
uh and then from that institutional
basis
we worked on different environmental
regimes it was that generation of
of environmental awareness
throughout the region and
using new mechanisms of law and policy
but always practicing
them and also you know participating in
the process towards the earth summit
on environment and development i want to
come to that in a sec
just just so i understand the the remit
of the foundation a bit better
it was focused on helping um
changes in policy and law and across
latin america to include
the the conversation about environmental
protection
and wise resource use in in the in the
legal system or
right during those times and also the
mechanisms
you know um because on the one hand you
have
you know the regimes the regimes for say
foreign conservation national national
parks or
or you know species conservation or
water quality or air pollution you have
these
like segments we were all organized by
segments during those times
you see i mean we all come at least i
come from that
you know the logic of here is the
environment and here's
you know social development and here's
the economy i hadn't integrated anything
although intuitively that was what i
wanted
you see but i didn't know how to do it
so i would just focus
on you know very concrete lineal
responses
to concrete problems you see so and
and my responses always done with others
was uh you know through legal
uh instruments and regimes now some of
them
like you know the three the three prince
the principles of access you know access
to justice access to information and
access to
uh decision making we knew at least
that anyone would like to use them for
their own purposes
so gradually we started interacting with
movements
that had other causes like you know
poverty uh uh gender equality
and and you know indigenous rights and
and gradually we started noticing that
they
really liked the idea of using exactly
the same mechanisms that
were being in institutionalized and
implemented
because of environmental aims see
so so it was very interesting and that
led me
of course personally to start
empathizing with the causes of others
because
these were all beautiful people they
were all you know
fighting for for you know a better world
uh but i had no clue and during those
times
i was very much a professional you know
i had a discipline my self
self security as a individual
was to know about the content
of a discipline i knew the scope of the
discipline
i would specialize i would you know
i would build my professional prestige
and reputation
based on my knowledge and
i would read books and i would write
that was me during those times and um
and i was you know i was recognized by
others and people would
would call me in people would pay for me
and so on and so you that then probably
led to
you being invited to um pulling together
the latin american um collaboration
in preparation for the earth summit in
rio
well let's put it this way you know
again uh but the person with whom we
worked
you know we had co-founded
and myself by nature both of us
are entrepreneurs so it's not we were
not invited
formally at the beginning but we started
proposing the activity so we started
actually coming up with initiatives
and we started clustering the different
alliances
from mexico all the way down to chile
and argentina
which was a civil society initiative
we were not called by the u.n for
example
but once you start doing that as we all
know
once you start calling all the parties
uh then the
and also the governments the local
governments the national government
then of course the next you know the
next
uh grouping or the intergovernmental
organization so we start
you know working with them so with a
bruntland commission with
um well with the un's secretariat for
the earth summit
uh there was a man called maurice strong
and the person who was in charge of
uh thus the relationships
of the u.n summit with
civil society was yolanda kakabazi
and uh she had been formerly the uh
the founder of the nattura foundation in
ecuador
and she was part of this process you see
and and then she was named the u.n under
secretary
for the relationships with civil society
so so it was natural it was like a
natural evolution because we started
to work on the preparations uh
well way back i can't remember exactly
the
the date but i would say like three
years before
you know preparing preparing you know uh
preparing
journalism preparing ngos preparing the
different sectors
labor union business uh
government you know preparing for
conversations and and
and there was uh our there was like
a report which was called our common
future i know this is
you know old history and uh history
so so so we started participating in you
know with
with contributions and and uh
yeah trillions of initiatives which were
you know catalyzed by by this process it
wasn't the only process
you see and this was this is very
important to say it was
one of the civil society processes that
fed into the earth summit you see so
i met maurice and hannah a number of
times because they
particularly hannah strong was also
quite involved in helping to start
or what was one of the founding members
of the global eco village network
and and those conversations and um
i've often often wondered because
maurice uh
put a lot of money into helping to
organize
the rio 92 summit but but how how did
what was his role actually in in
orchestrating
well he was the secretary of the
conference he was the general secretary
of the entire conference so it was the
process
and the the celebration of the
process and um
there's so many names that suddenly
start popping out
um yeah there was a there was a
a group in in geneva that i'm trying to
recall the name of the chap who passed
away anyway
um uh i mean
we we had the support of different
governments we had the support of uh
scandinavian governments in fact
plus the netherlands and uh and then
the the inter-american development bank
um
so we we had like a very strong support
of you know the brazilian government
but then the then brazilian government
and uh so so
everything sort of you know was a good
flow
and um so it was a good experience but
that experience in my personal journey
led me definitely to start saying you
know
i need to go beyond the discipline and
beyond the sector
you know i'm not i'm not a person that i
can fit in
my own borders so so i
realized that i had to go beyond and uh
it was then
that we met with with the founder of the
arena
foundation stefan schmidhini the swiss
philanthropist
and we had them again like one of my
most amazing conversations in my life
understanding the you know the the
reason for which he was creating uh
the foundation which was very simple he
would say
you know the the direction the course
on which we are will actually
make humanity you know crash into the
iceberg
so he wrote a book called changing
course
and he said we do have the opportunity
to change the course
we're still on time i'm i'm speaking
about 1996
yeah now and he said however
nobody knows how to now the collective
intelligence
definitely surely will know
and the way to do that is identifying
leadership
from any domain any field
so that's how we need to actually
approach it
it's not me a philanthropist that will
know what to do it's not the
organization
avina that will know what to do
leadership
in their interaction with the lenses
of sustainability long-term goals
you know commitment with lots of people
creativity
innovations towards the towards
sustainability
during those times sustainable
development in general and
that's what we need to do so the purpose
of arena
the founding purpose of arena was to
identify leadership
from any any sector any grouping
from the poverty from the wealth from
business from
any kind of ngo from wherever you see
identify them and see if we can match
with them
and make a partnership and then connect
them
for collective action so i was
i was completely you know
blown out with this new opportunity
because it matched exactly with what was
happening to me
and it was the moment that i started you
know like
uh feeling off my my my
older skin you see my discipline the
caterpillar turned into a butterfly and
you've been
hearing exactly that ever since with
lots of different
initiatives exactly and that was
amazing i just because we're talking
about stefan schmidt heine and um and
i have a connection somehow
to his story because he also spent a
good part of his life here on majorca
and still owns a large property of
mallorca
and then he had to kind of uh go to
latin america for legal reasons
um for a while and did the whole story
of his life of
of inheriting a huge amount of money and
and leadership of a large company
that um has probably created one of the
most environmentally or of
to human hearts most toxic products that
that
caused in like a huge amount of deaths
i personally lost a friend to asbestosis
um
how like if you knew him personally um
how was how did that affect him because
i mean it's a it's a
it's a huge karma to live with to on the
one hand have all this wealth
but to to know that i mean nobody in his
family
tried to kill people they they just
didn't know about the effects of this
this product but nevertheless all that
wealth that that he inherited was
somehow
generated by asbestos and
um how how did he
live or how does he live with this this
tension of on the one i mean he's done
enabled wonderful things through arena
and other
other things he's been a very active
philanthropist um
but it must be just a very difficult
thing to live with
that same conversation that we had in
again very very profound he
brought up the issue to me
like saying well you know
telling me about his own personal story
like saying and and this is my
interpretation of what
how i was perceiving him at that moment
right
[Music]
and he said to me you know
my parents you know basically
uh anticipated the inheritance
when i was i think he was 27
and uh a kid with all kinds of dreams
for a better world
um and suddenly
i i read an article
i'm not sure in which you know like
science or one of those
journals about asbestos
and i became aware
that i could become a mass criminal
right so
his decision was to find
a solution an alternative
and he was the man who actually came up
with the
alternative technologies and became an
activist to ban asbestos
[Music]
and that of course you went to the board
of the company with a plan which was not
accepted so he said
i need to i need to go i need to leave
because i can't be
coherent with my values and my vision of
the world i want
with this with this with this
uh what i have inherited
so that's when he started to sell his
cars
you see gradually it's a huge it was a
huge huge
conglomerate so
and i think that the fact that he was so
open
about his activism against uh
asbestos and creating of course all the
mechanisms for compensation
that he could think of in the different
parts of
where the company was i think that has
been
one of the grounds of
why he can be legally accused because he
knew
although there was no legislation
against uh asbestos
all the factories were legally
authorized
and uh he was i mean the company was
operating
under a legal you know uh legal
uh confirmation i mean everything was
okay from a legal
compliance yeah compliance exactly and
the world health
organization had still during those
times you know asbestos as
uh authorized substance so
it's but we all know that legally
speaking
even if you are legally authorized and
all the science says it's fine
if you acknowledge that it's not fine
that's one of the legal grounds for
accusations that's interesting because i
often wondered what was the the actual
legal loophole that that put him into
this position where
because he was also doing very good work
here on majorca and supporting a lot of
european
activities in the environmental area but
then
there was this time when when he
literally had to flee um
europe in order not to get um
incarcerated
well he actually did not flee from
europe he actually lives in switzerland
and the swiss government uh
actually understands his case and
protects him legally
so um but this is one of the
cases that if succeeds
it will be a terrible case for other
business
people in the world that suddenly
realize
that what they're doing is not good for
the planet
and for people if they actually
become activists of the change
of their own you know uh yeah their own
companies
make amends of their own mistakes that
they did right no
they become exactly persecuted so what
happened to me when i
listened to to him i think i was
even more moved by him because someone
who could be
that level of humbleness
you know and and and completely
dedicated
to do his part actually moved me
very very strongly and that was the
moment
that we built trust a kind of trust
that he said would you like to accompany
me
to start the advena foundation in latin
america
i said of course i mean it was like
a dream that i was i mean i couldn't
believe that this was true
[Music]
but it wasn't only the opportunity that
i received from stefan
but his wisdom i mean i've i've
understood so much of reality
just being with him but i also
understood by him
the importance or the potential
agent of change that could be
business i'm speaking you know in 1996
right no during those times it wasn't
i mean i i i didn't buy into
corporate social responsibility you see
i just couldn't
because i could sense something else
during those times
of course there's all kinds of
businesses but what i
did understand was the potential of
business leadership
business leadership not only
implementing that leadership for change
within the companies but to take
that example to the world
and so it was my very first moment in
life
that i had a grasp of uh intuition
that perhaps markets the market dynamics
could change if business would evolve
through their leadership of course at
the beginning during those times i was
still with the idea of
individual leaders you know i could see
someone like stefan as
my leader you see but of course then i
started you know evolving towards
collective leadership
thanks to the practice in arena and then
gradually you start you know
then you start evolving and and today i
would say that
every human being could be a leader a
leader
bringing their you know singular
singular originality to the world
and then you expand that and that's why
i feel that we need an economy and a
politics
that enables people to expand in and
flourish into all of
their dimensions and whenever i see
someone
you know constrained from being a leader
for society
regardless their ideas regardless the
context
then i feel the entire society is
missing
an opportunity and the planet as well
because humans are part of you know
resonating
uh living beings uh of life
so so when when you helped to set up
arena
for latin america and then in different
latin american countries from from
there on did arena just enabled lots of
environmental
projects environmental protection
projects through funding or
what was the the models operandi um
no it wasn't i mean no no no
aveda was not only about environmental
it was
social it was uh human rights it was
any domain of leadership
see and it was basically trying to
connect all the dimensions what we
refer to as the uh triple impact value
creation
during those times we would say
intersectorial you know
we would say sustainable development uh
but sustainable development in latin
america was not
associated and narrowed down only to the
environment
sustainable development in our language
was mostly
uh the integration our language and our
vision in latin america in general was
the integration of all the dimensions
and whatever you would do you see so it
was social
environmental and economically
sustainable
and uh and and politically sustainable
as well you know and culturally
sustainable it was the
in you know that's very unique i would
say of the
latin american uh cosmic vision
um that's very present so
so and how would you achieve that if you
were an environmental leader
and you would need a social leader the
interaction
would actually be based on the
mutual admiration of leadership of
commitment and engagement
and then you start cooperating and then
you start integrating by
people to people you see so uh
so that was the logic the dynamics of
aveeno
and uh is that also why because
when you started to work with others on
creating system away
and you you already understood
that be corporations by themselves
only as a few companies trying to do
things a little bit better or even um
improving um wasn't
wasn't going to cut it and because
how how would you distinguish how
because in europe we don't really have
like there's a pretty strong b corp
movement
but um the systemic approach
apart from a few grassroots landing
points like nessie in
in in spain um hasn't really landed yet
the
the vision that i understand you hold
with systemabe
to work with lawyers to work in policy
to work with business to work with civil
society to
to literally create the human
connections that human
mutual recognition you just spoke about
that should business as usual fail which
we both know
it will or already is that there is a
an infrastructure of predominantly human
relationships and
trust that can buffer
the collapse of a system that no longer
serves is is that right
it's very correct um although what
happened was that
2009 was a very uh um
very significant year for me because i
was in
stockholm uh and i heard for the first
time
from johann uh rockstrom
roster oh thank you uh
at the stockholm uh resilience center
um the state of health
of the earth of the planet and for the
first time in my life i heard
the notion of ecosystem planetary
boundaries
[Music]
um i remember i was sitting down
and suddenly had it was an aha moment
so i looked back to see if others were
having the same feeling
if i was the only one and i started
for a big you know period of time
a moment of anguish of not knowing what
to do
because i started realizing the scale of
the problem
in which we were that same year
was cop
13. in
in copenhagen i think yeah that's a
disaster yeah
so i went to copenhagen and of course i
saw
well there were many things that
happened and and i noticed
how the delegations were each of them
protecting their national interests
[Music]
and at the same time i could see because
i knew some of
the private business sectors you know
interacting with the national delegation
and i started feeling well
where are we going to speak about the
common general good for humanity and the
planet
in this conversation this is something
about negotiating who's going to be
seeding uh confronted with whom china
the us
india anyway i started feeling
the lack of a space
that would give me the trust to say this
is what we work
for the common good of all humanity and
the planet
and for a few years or a few months i
would say
or a year more or less i started sensing
the lack of a space
where i would feel if i do this
it's going to be contributing to a
solution
and uh so that was when i started my own
second crisis of you know a
lifetime not that i had a problem with
arena but i suddenly felt aveena is not
enough
then suddenly i realized you know
another aha moment business is the most
numerous
of all human organizations after family
and the most numerous of everyday
decisions
are a commercial nature
so i had this flash and so and at that
moment
alex fryer who was one of the founders
actually the
founding foul the the inspirational
founder
of guayaqui the giro mate
beveridge energy drink beverage
approached to me and he said let's talk
about guayaquil
and let's talk about you know our aim
and how we want to achieve that age
of regenerating the forest and the sense
of communities
that dwell in those southern atlantic
forests in brazil argentina and paraguay
and that we couldn't achieve it in a
financially sustainable
manner through the market so it was a
market driven
solution so started experiencing that
and i decided to become a small
shareholder
with that act i started experiencing
a journey of one company
so immediately i started calling to my
friends all over south america like
saying
hey do you know of other companies that
do similar stuff
you know others that do regeneration
regeneration was my response
to the trespassing of ecosystem
planetary boundaries
and and and so so that was my lineal
thinking
you see so as it went away what do we do
so it comes back and people can still
be there and and flourish there so that
was my
interconnection if you want when i
started calling
my friends i called
basically friends from chile colombia
brazil
argentina i started noticing that
perhaps
very few some few companies had
exactly the same goal as as guayatu
regeneration of deserts uh
other other forests but in brazil
and but in chile they didn't have the
same kind of companies
with that same goal i'm speaking
about my uh 2010
and 2000 uh early 2011 right
but in chile a very close friend of mine
my emilia correa
said i don't know of any company that
wants regeneration but i'm starting to
see
other companies that have converted a
societal needs
into their purpose into their business
purpose
and their new core business you see and
they're taking that purpose
to every single act
like how they source their you know with
their supplies how they sell
how they attract investors how they
attract collaborators this is very new
what we're
what we're observing so
and she said well we might start
something new right
i said let's start something
and i was actually lecturing you know
once you start
becoming passionate about a new vision
you know you're still developing it you
start sharing that
so you know i started sharing this in
different
you know presentations and lectures i
was in the university
in buenos aires in the taylor university
and someone from the audience said but
this is already existing in my country
and that was the u.s the big corpse
yes and they're called the big courts
and that was at
seven o'clock in the afternoon and this
is quite relevant
so i immediately went to talk to this
man
after the lecture and i said do you know
more about this he said yes i know the
founders i know the creators
and and i said can we meet with them
well that night i went out
with people i went back home and the
first thing i did
was to write the mail to my emilia
correa
and that the moment that did the click
i received the mail from my career
with the same link about b lab and b
quotes
like saying we need to meet these people
i said i've just
met i now know how to do that it was
that moment
and so three months we started
conversations with the founders
of b lab and the creators of the b
chords and i always say you know the
moment of co-creation
is the most sacred moment that comes
from
multiple multiple energies and knowledge
and
experiences and they suddenly become
crystallized
in a new innovation and that's why i
always celebrate the three founders
of avila uh bart houlihan
jay cohen and and and andrew kasoy
i always celebrate them because thanks
to that
we were able to expand the systems
approach we went to new york we fell in
love with them
four latin americans and the three u.s
americans
we just became like so brothers and
sisters
and we said we're gonna make it but when
we got
back to latin america that those
following two months we decided that we
were gonna
create what we call system b not system
a but system b
why because in latin america we had a
concept
of polarization of lots of divisions
left right poor rich who are the ones to
blame
and who are the good guys and we thought
we need to create a new
safe space to engage people from
all avenues and where we are not
stuck with the wording in fact the name
comes because of our lack of
intelligence and inspiration to put
a name of what kind of system we wanted
because
every word that we found had
the baggage of a historical
conflict and we said no more let's put b
and if it doesn't work eventually it'll
become c
you see but we needed something you know
that would
invite everybody to a safe space
and that's the reason for which we
thought everywhere where we start
system b has to start with concrete
you know examples of equals becoming
sorry companies becoming big courts
because it's a very concrete way to
prove that business can
actually be part of you know large-scale
solutions
and so that's i would say that's a
pillar that's the the pillar of any
system b
now say any system b because today you
have uh
ten national system b's and then you
have one which is
system b international and then you have
local b communities
at that can be provincial or state
level or can be city wise so
that's quite that's that's the logic but
everywhere where we start
we start with a call because once you
have the examples then
you start triggering all the other
groups it's
very common for people to say shouldn't
we have to be politicians
or should we have the be lawyers or
shouldn't we have to be
educators i mean shouldn't we have the b
by understanding the b in the vision of
what's in the perception has to do with
integrated value creation
accountability and transparency and and
what value the way you produce value
and how you go beyond the share
value and how you go beyond the
shareholder privacy
so the shareholder priority if you want
towards like all groupings and old
stakeholders
to be able to to balance the interest of
all the groups
right and in the short term in the long
term
these elements are appealing to
everybody
it's not only appealing to business so
what we decided to do
sorry i'm just wondering whether in
these national
sub chapters of systemabe
um you start with
working with the b corps in that
locality
but then this this opening up towards
civil society towards
policymakers towards law how how do you
do
are all of those 10 national
um system away and not just
business based but across all three
sectors
involving um civil society uh
politics governance all that yeah
it's very organic you start with
business
an event you know the first vehicle was
the one founded by one of the founders
of site
[Music]
uh another one was founded by another of
the founders
another one was also co-founded by
myself
so latte was in chile three sql started
in
chile so so you know we we were the
first
generation of b corps in latin america
and
so so we worked with business that was
our first priority
because we believed on the on business
as a
force for good you see that's very
concrete
now we knew that the lawyers
lawyers and accountants are the well
basically lawyers are
because of risk management are the first
to be called by the ceo
and by the boards right so we thought
hey let's share this with a law firm
sorry not with the law firm
with lawyers and the leaders from the
law firms
this is a leadership approach you see
so what happened what that some of the
lawyers started getting passionate about
this new opportunity
of impact law so that's how
he started to to see the emergence
of a now a very strong
and very successful network of
the lawyers it's called the latin
american
impact lawyers network right
and working always globally because
situate was
born in chile but with the global
aspiration i mean we were suddenly
realizing that there was something that
we could share with the world
so everything that we would do would
have to be
uh valid for anywhere in the world
so that was the systems approach right
so
the assist the the six communities i
would say
large broad communities that has the
system being modeled
as first the pillar of vehicles then the
large market players and these are
by and large a large company
very large companies the governments in
the market
uh role and consumer
consumer associations large consumer
associations
large chunks of interest there
then and and as a result of that of that
approach for example this large second
category you have large companies
walking towards becoming b corps
right because the logic is not for all
companies to become vehicles the logic
is for
all companies to conduct their business
as if they were be caught you see
so it's it's trying to move
the market in that direction in creating
value and solution
also another example so now today
you have over in latin america you have
over 15 000 companies
and you have lots of them experimenting
either individually or together the what
we call
camino marie which is a program for a
large company
and you also have a program for the
value chain
so so or initiatives this is a process
of engaging large companies that if they
were to try
to go through the classic certification
process to become a b corp they would
definitely fail
at their current performance but in
order to be able to engage them
in the process of learning you've opened
up that
that right we'll walk with you right
yeah and and and of course you have this
first element
which is the purpose how to make purpose
a
living energy for the entire market but
through the business
the second element has to do with
measuring
and well evaluate assessing and
measuring your
your impact in different areas
and then the third main element has to
do with expanding your
fiduciary liability uh going beyond the
share
share shareholder value shareholders
privacy
to all the stakeholder interests what
we call today the stakeholder governance
right
this is the state the whole system is
the stakeholder governance
now with those elements you still can
uh attract many large companies
in the direction in that direction i
mean the huge the largest companies
so um but of course we're very happy
when
some of these become vehicles like
nature was for many years the largest
b corp in the world uh now it's
uh way in the u.s and
more than 40 percent of its uh sales are
under the b
corp structure now globally speakers
but that i was just referring to the
second uh
i would say uh community of practice the
large companies that they also meet
they help each other they use the same
uh tools of
assessment once you use the same tool of
assessment
then you start the same kind of
conversations about your relationship
with the workers your relationship with
the suppliers with your clients with
their communities
with the the level of governance that
you have accountabilities
and then you start getting these
conversations
on board in the market in society
you see so so once you have these
programs
that's what starts happening now at the
same time you have the governments
once these get on board they start
realizing
that they could also source or they
could have
procurement regimes that would promote
the emergence of this new
business identity this new business uh
sector if you want because if you think
about it
it's exactly the same goals of politics
are you know embedded in these companies
in the b course
the same higher goals i would say the
same higher
objectives of politics right so suddenly
you start seeing hey we can
have large-scale solutions through
business and the market dynamics because
once business starts operating this way
then the clients can operate this way
and then the suppliers and so on the
investors and the collaborators
so you start driving into this move
you know many many other players now
and and the case is that mendoza was the
first city that adopted that regime
but that regime wasn't inspired medellin
so now in latin america you have two
cities that
have done the same in terms of uh
developing procurement regimes that
uh bet not only benefit but create
the market for this kind of business
right so so it's what we call high
impact
business right is it i mean this was one
of the questions i had for you that
i certainly find here in europe um like
a number of times now i've been invited
to um sort of business breakfasts or
business lunches to talk about
regenerative culture and regenerative
development and and
of course all these more and more
companies are beginning to be very
interested in how can i get a piece of
regenerative um and and become a
regenerative company
but my personal sense is that um
there's a sort of glass ceiling of what
you can do as a business leader
particularly if you
run a publicly listed company it's
different
for a patagonia or um
or guayaqui or those companies or lush
or dr bonner and that are also
pretty big companies not as big as these
giants but
um but because they're not shareholder
obliged
in the same way they can make decisions
much in a much more agile way
but um like if you look paul pullman's
path with unilever he
he brought up a whole bunch of b-corps
as unilever
um but eventually he kind of realized
that that he wasn't going to be able
to transform unilever as a whole
and that that i i sense that as long as
the
political regulation playing field and
also the current conditions of how we
set incentives
in markets and how we organize our
economy
um aren't transformed there's only so
much that
that even the largest companies could
possibly do and certainly smaller
companies
yeah you're absolutely right absolutely
right
uh although one can still do something
to move in that direction so those some
things for example the network of
lawyers
in the case of brazil has been working
sorry impact lawyers right has been
working with another of our communities
the academic community
you know professors that start observing
this and start creating from
academics you know solutions i know and
also with
um vehicles and also with com
large companies listed companies like
natura once you have one
case then you say it's true and it can
happen so natura is a listed company
that has opened up all the answers to
all the questionnaire of the b impact
assessment
so so and it's very moving to see
how they present themselves as an with
their imperfection
but with their engagement and commitment
to improvement
and how they start moving ahead on a
regular basis
and and they go through different
resatification processes
every three years now what happened in
in brazil is very interesting with the
stock market
the rules of the stock market and the
sao paulo stock market which is a large
stock
stock market uh has adopted
the the the the questionnaire
of the be impact assessment for the
listed companies
it doesn't mean that it you're obliged
to
become a vehicle but once that's why for
me
it's very important to understand the
value
of the impact measurement
uh some people think
it's only to get a certification you
know the brand would be with a
with a circle certified uh
benefit corporation but it's not that
it's not only that sorry it means it
changes the way people think
it's it's it's exactly what buckminster
fuller said don't tell people what to
think give them a tool the use of which
will change the way they
think and by asking people questions
which is why i have 250 questions in my
book
um you you restructure their thinking
you invite them into whole new
connections that they previously didn't
have
and so a well-structured questionnaire
exactly
so so just imagine if to be to become a
listed company in a stock market
you have to ask yourself some questions
it's very simple and then
it's very simple it's it's it's witty
and and but it's the kind of you know
it's the kind of conversations that we
need
that we normally had outside business we
had it in politics in academics in
in civil society but we didn't have it
inside
business so that's why for me that that
tool
the be impact assessment tool
which is reviewed you know on a regular
basis as well and it's always improved
and it's always stronger it's
sorry more strict that tool is not
only useful for the for the
certification
it's useful as a management tool that
helps
management to become much more
sustainable
in terms of connecting all the dots
to become systemic because one of the
pillars of sustainability
is to become systemic and
and you know before we
associated um business
as the most pragmatic because if you're
not pragmatic you don't survive
yet we come from the lineal pragmatism
how do we evolve from lineal thinking
and practice
pragmatism to systemic pragmatism
and and and that's something that i
appreciate very much from this tool
which is socratic
as you say remember socrates would ask
you questions in the market in the aggro
not in you know with the acropolis and i
think that's brilliant
you see these are the questions where
you can interact with the totality
in the market this is where we can
actually take those questions
to the everyday commercial decisions you
see
so it's a educational tool
a conversational good quality
conversational tool
and of course you know it's a management
tool and a certification tool
you see so so it has many many
attributes
for me at least and those that too
have been useful for academics to ask
the same questions
in business schools you know academia b
has been created
not only for latin america it started in
latin america but now you have
professors in all the continents
and uh and that was very useful for the
cities you know the movement that cities
can be
started in rio de janeiro earlier you
referred to six legs
can you can you just name the section
okay sorry sorry
you don't miss the passion out of one of
them yeah daniel i get passionate
speaking of about this yeah the b cook
community the large market players
with governments whether governments
large companies and consumers
then you have the academics the
knowledge building
block or community of practices then you
have a civil society in general
and and you have many many movements
that are stemming out from that
and then you have the investment world
and then the uh government has regulated
um so so these are the six communities
and and everything that we do includes
you know well at the very beginning when
you start a
this model you start only with b quotes
but um
but then you start seeing what happens
with the others and
and it's very contagious uh so the
systems are being
adopted by different communities of
people uh which are combined
uh you know combined multi-stakeholder
uh groupings uh but they find the market
as the space for uh
society large scale solutions social
environmental solutions
now personally i still have the passion
for regeneration
the integrated regeneration so as a
small investor
you know i push regeneration as an
example everywhere
and and i'm very happy to see that many
many
companies are also starting to think
regeneration
as their own purpose and regeneration is
a integrated notion
it's not only ecological regeneration
because it's
you know it's the region regeneration
for example myself
you know of my different parts that i
had separated
in my life but i now feeling that i have
united the bits and pieces which were
separate in my mind
obviously given my context given my
culture
you see but then when you see for
example
when you see the results you know almost
sixty thousand
um well sixty thousand acres acres
almost two hundred hundred thousand
acres
no sixty thousand hectares regenerated
of of uh the south atlantic forest
brazil argentina and uh paraguay
which were impoverished and they have
come back to life
more than a thousand families that are
living together with
you know food sovereignty uh with living
incomes um but not only with that with
you know with empowerment of being
themselves
just one tip there with the kovitz
one of the ethnic groups the aceh
in paraguay had produced
a harvest of 2 800 kilos
with organic food and you know
vegetables and fruit
and donated to the slum
dwellers of asuncion you see
there you can see what it means in in
concrete
you see but then again going back to
waiakea
as a company i'm not saying it's kuayaki
that actually achieved these results
it's sourcing from
indigenous communities sourcing from
campesino communities
cooperatives you know they're the ones
who actually are doing that
part you see uh then when you sell the
products
of you know gerba mate uh
based products in the product uh
markets canada the us and chile then you
see that
the clients become you know also the the
stakeholders who actually achieve that
solution
then you find investors investors and of
course you have all kinds of investors
and you have the investors which are the
typical impact investors that
actually converge the purpose and the
solutions
with a business model let me be
quite direct i mean after six years of
investment
uh and i hope i find it a little bit
difficult to say this
but the share value of my shares went up
now i never aimed at such a
difference you see it wasn't my logic
but
i'm i feel comfortable with the idea
that in this case it's not financial
speculation
it's basically societal valuation
expressed in the value of the sheriff
this is what i i
i that's a really nice way of saying
that the switch of
the investment mentality that that
should occur
right so and then you see that you know
the purpose the regeneration purpose the
integrated
the life regeneration purpose of waikiki
it's a journey
because you know their carbon footprint
was being affected
by the the distribution of the products
so they created
a company for distribution and they
bought
253 eb
bolt vehicles for the last mile you see
and you know who are the drivers it's
amazing
it's ex-convicts and yeah
and who are the ones who actually
communicate the the the results and the
purpose of goyaki
you know there's no guayaquil pays from
40 to 60
more the market value to the to the
suppliers you know indigenous
communities and campesinos
and they compete with red food and and
and
how does that happen because what
happens is that
everybody becomes a competency a
positive competency to
for that goal so just imagine 2 000
volunteers
students at university campuses you know
communicating the same purpose having a
concrete example
of how you achieve it through the market
and then you have the musicians you know
the platform
come to life music that you have the
musicians
communicating the same purpose so once
you start
seeing the extent of the
infinite that you can reach out
just by being a good business
for society and the planet it's
very inspiring for so many other
thousands of players
in the market so that's why i feel
that if you have the examples
you catalyze all the other groups you
see
all the other groups of a system but if
you don't have the example
it could be very theoretical so
just like i shared the example of
guayaquil
i can also show you the exam many many
other examples
of other main industries
restaurant chains with cleaning up
oceans or uh inclusion of
you know uh single mothers in the in the
market in the labor market
or special services for those slums or
you know you have so many purposes so
many purposes
as human intercourse so many purpose
as human responses to social or societal
needs and
planetary needs so that's the what i'm
seeing from everywhere from government
officials
from investors from academics from now
the accountants are starting to
build their own community um from
lawyers from the
youth yeah the cities that start at this
moment of cities can be
in rio and now it's already in edinburgh
and barcelona
you see so so you can see that anything
that we can do from
anywhere in the world can be useful
for the entire human humanity and the
economy and the market is one
[Music]
and humanity as well unfortunately we've
only got another five minutes left but i
i'd be interested in in this networked
approach
of um obviously
you can't build a system like that in in
a relatively short period of time or a
network of networks
and acros spanning across an entire
subcontinent
and beyond into europe and other places
um without letting go
of the notion of having to triple check
that every new
partner that you work with is doing
everything perfectly exactly how you
would do it
so you need to find very
light enabling constraints and basic
agreements on how to proceed so
a new system away in a new country
doesn't end up being something
completely contradictory to
the the mission and how do you achieve
that building the trust in the network
and rolling
like expanding the network um and at the
same time
maintaining some form of quality control
that what people do
as you let them go they call you up and
say we're thinking about starting
so that is can be cities can be um
how do you how do you make sure that
that then is actually something
that that you still feel aligned with
and that that is aligned with the
impulse
yeah daniel excellent question you know
when you start
you have mousse but along the way you
start having
a legal agreement you see the mlus are
self law the legal agreements
are you know you can execute them now
there's one thing which has been again
the pillar
we have a licensing agreement c2a
international has a licensing
agreement with b lab and vehicles are
vehicles
you see and and there's no way benefit
corporation the legal status is a
benefit corporation throughout the world
so we have something similar called
society beneficiary
it's the same legal language the same
legal elements that that's
being pushed so we have agreements with
that
and uh to be assured that
you know we that's not uh that's not
effective
in its nature regarding system b
we all acknowledge that depending on the
context he starts
in a different pace you see brazil was
much more
proactive with the b corps than the
large sorry building the b corp
community
and especially with the large companies
brazil has huge companies
and they were very successful there uh
other countries started
more with smes but they all start with
that
and there is a there was an mmu and now
you start having
a much more sophisticated a design of
of agreements legal agreements for these
new movements
and uh and and this this is going to be
a challenge all the time because
suddenly have an innovation like
yesterday two days ago
i was speaking to a group of journalists
like saying hey we would like to do
something similar
with the with a group of building a
community of journalists
from throughout the region to to
learn together how to be good
observance of this
i would say the economic tradition
evolution
you know uh so so called the economic
innovation
called the impact economy but you know
they're not so many
journalists that have developed the
lenses
to be able to com to understand and
communicate this
i mean i'm speaking about massively
because the logic is for
any journalist to be able to communicate
this well
now the best way of doing it was would
be with the leadership of the
journalists
so this is happening everywhere
yesterday i was in a webinar
and someone from mexico said hey we
should do something for the be
educators at the you know the elementary
school
and so on but now you're starting the
community of the bee entrepreneurs
you see so so you start this emerging
everywhere
once you have the systems approach
what's beautiful about a system model
is that you know that whatever is done
by one end of the system
will benefit the other end and will
synergize with the other end
and of course it's benefiting not only
for inside the system but it's together
for the world and for the planet so you
see
it's so the achievements of one part are
considered
the achievements of any of the other
parts you see
so that's the logic of the systems
approach and of course
once you drive this through trade once
you have one community here
they meet with others here they start
trade
and it's an impact trade and then if
it's from different countries
we start having international impact
trade
so so trade agreements have to do with
creating solutions for the other
end of the of the trade value chain
you see and so on and and this goes on
and on it's a
it's a beautiful evolutionary experience
and and so is your journey thank you so
much for this this conversation
it's really inspiring and and i i feel
that
there's more and more wind building in
the sales of
what you and and collaborators in the
sistema bay movement have
have um like you've set the sails but
the wind's definitely blowing in your
favor now um
where everybody is really looking for
alternatives and also for alternative
recoveries from
from the pandem pandemic and um
i i see like talking to you makes me
hopeful and
and that's uh that's great because
there are so many stories on the planet
at the moment that don't make you
hopeful
so thank thank you so much for the
conversation and and i hope we can have
another one because
i don't think this one is finished yet
thank you
i'm always available and also talking to
you it's like
always finding bright spots in in in the
universe
and and thank you for the kind of work
that you do uh
you're inspiring you know thousands
thousands of people
all over the world wow thank you daniel
thank you
and talk to you soon lots of love all
the best huh
all the best thank you